Guide to the Joseph St. Leger d'Happart Papers, 1768-1815 DAR.1957.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Joseph St. Leger d'Happart Papers
1768-1815
ULS Archives & Special Collections
D'Happart, J. L. (Joseph Leger)
DAR.1957.01
7.17 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
Joseph St. Leger d'Happart was a French immigrant and naturalized citizen of the United States engaged in mercantile imports to the United States from Suriname (Dutch Guiana) and France. D'Happart was imprisoned for debts to a French business partner from 1807 to 1808. The collection includes letters from Thomas Jefferson, Albert Gallatin and James Madison. This collection of around 2,000 items documents d'Happart's personal and business life, including his estrangement and divorce from his wife, and his mercantile ventures. Much of the collection is in English, but some family and business correspondence is in French, and many documents related to his travels to Suriname are in Dutch.
Biography
Joseph St. Leger d'Happart spent eighteen months in a French prison before immigrating to the United States. D'Happart claimed to have served Louis XVI, but the voracity of this claim is dubious. He arrived in Boston early in 1796 and obtained United States citizenship. D'Happart became a clerk in 1797, but he soon quarreled with his employers. D'Happart married Elizabeth Thompson, daughter of Brigadier General William Thompson (c.1725 to 1781) of New Castle, Delaware. According to materials in the collection, the couple had at least three children, including an oldest son and a daughter. D'Happart and his wife lived in New Castle for a short time, and subsequently resided throughout Pennsylvania. D'Happart made his living in the mercantile business, and was involved in a variety of colorful international business ventures. Between 1798 and 1801, d'Happart made three trips to the Dutch colony of Suriname for the William & Read Co. and the Rocheteau firm.
From 1804 to 1805, d'Happart made an extended trip to France during which he arranged for the import of French goods which d'Happart, Joseph Thebeaud and Simon Chaudron & Co. sold in the United States. While in France, d'Happart met L. F. Babin, a Frenchman who assisted d'Happart in his lawsuit against the French government for the return of d'Happart's family property, which had been confiscated during the Revolution. D'Happart gave Babin power of attorney to complete the return of his property. D'Happart returned to the United States aboard his ship the Brig Betsy, of which L. F. Babin owned a quarter share. The ship was boarded by the British and taken to Newfoundland where all but a few items hidden by d'Happart were confiscated. In 1806, Babin accused d'Happart of owing him money. D'Happart was arrested in Pittsburgh in September of 1807, and taken to a Philadelphia debtor's prison to await trial. According to d'Happart's deposition, Babin sold d'Happart's French properties and fled France with the money. Furthermore, d'Happart claimed that he could account for all of the goods for which Babin claimed to be owed. The facts of this story remain unclear.
After his release from prison in June of 1808, d'Happart and his family lived in Philadelphia until October. They later moved to Chambersburg in early November, and settled at Somerset a month later. D'Happart and his wife separated in 1812, and Elizabeth was granted a divorce by the governor of Pennsylvania in 1815.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection of around 2,000 items documents d'Happart's personal and professional life. The majority of the collection is in English, but personal and some business correspondence are in French, and many documents related to his business in Suriname are in Dutch. The collection contains correspondence, ledgers, depositions, bound print materials, transcription books, note cards, and travel papers.
D'Happart's various residences are documented with personal and local business records, correspondence, and financial documents. D'Happart's personal papers consist of family correspondence, papers, and documents relating to his imprisonment, and his divorce. The Thompson family papers document the family of d'Happart's wife, Elizabeth Thompson. D'Happart's family correspondence includes letters from d'Happart's wife, Elizabeth, his sister Maria Read, and his niece, Henriette de St. Leger. D'Happart's personal papers also include documents and correspondence related to his estrangement and divorce from his wife, which are quite detailed about the acrimonious split.
D'Happart's failed French business ventures are documented, as well as his subsequent arrest in Pittsburgh and imprisonment in Philadelphia from 1807 to 1808 on a debtor's warrant issued by his French business partner, C. F. Babin, related to a ship they co-owned, the Brig Betsy. Business correspondence unrelated to his French partnerships is also present, including letters from Albert Gallatin and Thomas Jefferson concerning Indian Affairs and the Treasury, respectively.
A number of bound transcription books are also represented, containing handwritten copies of correspondence to and from d'Happart in English and French. These books seem to be the work of a nineteenth century family member. These transcription books are not comprehensive, and include family correspondence not contained in their original form elsewhere in this collection.
The collection also contains a number of published materials that were probably collected by d'Happart in the United States and France. These materials include literary magazines published in the United States in English and French, and two longer French language works. Finally, the collection includes a set of calendar cards created by library staff or a researcher of a portion of the d'Happart papers.
Arrangement
The papers have been arranged into nine series.
Series I. Residences in Pennsylvania, 1794-1815
Series II. Suriname, 1798-1802
Series III. General business correspondence, 1799-1812
Series IV. Rocheteau accounts, 1800-1808
Series V. French business ventures, confiscation of the Brig Betsy and debtors prison, 1804-1808
Series VI. Personal papers, 1800-1812
Series VII. Transcription books, 1800-1815
Series VIII. Published materials, 1807-1825
Series IX. Calendar cards
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of LeRoy d'Happart to the Darlington Memorial Library in 1957.
Previous Citation
Joseph St. Leger d'Happart Papers, 1768-1815, DAR.1957.01, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Custodial History
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Correspondence; Personal papers; Business records; Merchants -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania -- History -- 1775-1865; France -- History -- 19th century; France -- Description and travel; Suriname -- Description and travel; Debt, Imprisonment for -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Slavery -- United States -- History; Slavery -- North Carolina -- History; Slavery -- Maryland -- History; United States -- Commerce -- History; United States -- Economic conditions -- To 1865; France -- Commerce -- History; France -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Pennsylvania -- Commerce -- History; Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions -- History; Connellsville (Pa.) -- History; West Newton (Pa.) -- History; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- History; Somerset (Pa.) -- History; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- History; D'Happart, J. L. (Joseph Leger); Betsy (Schooner); Babin, L. F.; Thompson, Elizabeth; D'Happart family; Jefferson, Thomas
- Residences in Pennsylvania, 1794-1815; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  D'Happart first moved to the United States in 1796 as a young man. D'Happart lived in a number of towns throughout Pennsylvania, and seems to have lived in each location for only a few years. His various residences are documented with personal and local business records, correspondence, and financial documents. This series contains letters between d'Happart and his wife Elizabeth during his periods abroad, and letters to Elizabeth from various people to whom d'Happart owed money. These materials are written in English.
  - First residence in the United States, 1794-1799 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First residence in the United States, 1794-1799 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania, 1800-1802 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania, 1800-1802 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania, 1800-1802 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania, 1800-1802 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bristol Hill, Pennsylvania, 1802-1803 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bristol Hill, Pennsylvania, 1802-1803 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Connellsville, Pennsylvania, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Connellsville, Pennsylvania, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Robbstown, Pennsylvania, 1805-1806 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Robbstown, Pennsylvania, 1805-1806 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Robbstown, Pennsylvania, 1805-1806 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robbstown, Pennsylvania, 1805-1806 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1806-1807 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Somerset, Pennsylvania, 1808-1812 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Somerset, Pennsylvania, 1808-1812 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Jacob's Creek, Pennsylvania, 1809-1815 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Connellsville, Pennsylvania, May 1815 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scheme for lottery, Connellsville, Pennsylvania, November 20, 1815 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Land in Southwest Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Land in Southwest Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Land in Southwest Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Land plot, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Surinam, 1798-1802; II.
  D'Happart traveled to the Dutch colony of Surinam in South America in 1798, 1799 and 1801. He worked for the Rocheteau firm and the William & Read Co. Surinam's slave economy produced sugar and other raw goods. This series contains d'Happart's travel documents, papers related to his partnerships with Rocheteau and William & Read, as well as the state of his personal finances. Some of these documents are written in Dutch.
  Missing Title
  The collection also includes two bills of sale for slaves purchased by d'Happart. The first is for a thirteen-year-old slave purchased in New Hanover County, North Carolina on December 4, 1798, and the second for a thirty year old slave purchased in Maryland on February 19, 1799. It is unclear if these enslaved people were purchased for personal use, or for resale. Both bills of sale indicate that d'Happart is from Surinam.
  - Purchase of Slaves, 1798-1799 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Travel documents, 1798-1801 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rocheteau partnership, 1798-1801 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Rocheteau partnership, 1798-1801 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rocheteau partnership, 1798-1801 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Surinam, 1800-1801 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Surinam, 1800-1801 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - William & Read Co., 1800-1802 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - William & Read Co., 1800-1802 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Personal Accounts, 1798-1802 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Personal Accounts, 1798-1802 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Personal Accounts, 1798-1802 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- General Business Correspondence, 1799-1812; III.
  This series represents correspondence from various clients, partners, and lenders to d'Happart and relate to his business interests in the United States. In an 1809 letter, Albert Gallatin replies to d'Happart's letter, notifying him that the Indian Department, to which he had written, had been transferred to the Secretary of War. Another notable exchange between d'Happart and Thomas Jefferson in 1812 concerns an unpaid debt between d'Happart and the United States Treasury. Jefferson notifies d'Happart that he has referred the matter to President Madison. The majority of these materials are in written English, though a few letters are written in French.
  - William Cleland to d'Happart, 1799-1805 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - William Cleland to d'Happart, 1799-1805 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - William Cleland to d'Happart, 1799-1805 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Richard Caton to d'Happart, 1800 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - William Drummond to d'Happart, 1800 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Arch Grace to d'Happart, 1800 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - T. D. Houfft to d'Happart, 1800 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Boislandry to d'Happart, 1800-1801 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Boislandry to d'Happart, 1800-1801 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - George Barclay & Co. to d'Happart, 1801-1802 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Charles Gheguire to d'Happart, 1800-1801 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Charles Gheguire to d'Happart, 1800-1801 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - John McFadon to d'Happart, 1800-1801 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Willian Cooke to d'Happart, 1801 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Walter Dorsey to d'Happart, 1801 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - John Milner to d'Happart, 1801 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Joseph Warren to d'Happart, 1801 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - M. de Baizeto d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - M. de Baizeto d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Samuel Tredwell Edenton to d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Samuel Tredwell Edenton to d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - McKim to d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Alexis Teste to d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Alexis Teste to d'Happart, 1800-1802 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Le Bardier du plessis to d'Happart, 1801-1803 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Le Bardier du plessis to d'Happart, 1801-1803 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - J. T. Mason and William Simmons to d'Happart, 1800-1803 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - J. T. Mason and William Simmons to d'Happart, 1800-1803 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Smith & Buchanan to d'Happart, 1800-1803 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Smith & Buchanan to d'Happart, 1800-1803 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Robertson & Brown to d'Happart, 1800-1804 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Robertson & Brown to d'Happart, 1800-1804 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Henry Alexander to d'Happart, 1801-1805 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Henry Alexander to d'Happart, 1801-1805 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - John Truchet to d'Happart, 1805-1807 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - John Truchet to d'Happart, 1805-1807 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - John Truchet to d'Happart, 1805-1807 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - John Purviance to d'Happart, 1806 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - B. Bourne to d'Happart, 1806-1808 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - B. Bourne to d'Happart, 1806-1808 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Tucker Granger to d'Happart, 1809-1812 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Albert Gallatin to d'Happart, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - d'Happart to Jefferson and Jefferson to d'Happart, 1812 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Johns to d'Happart, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Johns to d'Happart, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Johns to d'Happart, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - d'Happart to Peter Locher, 1808 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - d'Happart to William Philson, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Robert Philson to d'Happart, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - d'Happart to Schneiders, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - d'Happart to James Clark, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808; IV.
  The Rocheteau firm was one of d'Happart's clients during a trip to Surinam, his travels in France, and time in the United States. This series includes the accounting ledgers of the company, and related correspondence. These materials are written variously in French and English. Box 7 in this series contains oversized materials, including d'Happart's passport and business papers. Also included, are accounts of his life and adventures that were published as a broadside in the eighteenth century.
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - The Pedestrian Tour (broadside) (Oversize 7, Folder 1)
  - d'Happart's Passport, January 1, 1798 (Oversize 7, Folder 2)
  - Business Information and copies, 1790-1800 (Oversize 7, Folder 3)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Rocheteau Accounts, 1800-1808 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- French business ventures, confiscation of the Brig Betsy and debtors prison, 1804-1808; V.
  From 1804 to 1805, d'Happart made an extended trip to France during which he arranged an import business. While in France, he partnered with L. F. Babin in the purchase of a ship, the Brig Betsy. Babin assisted d'Happart in reclaiming family property confiscated by the French revolutionary government. The Brig Betsy was boarded by the British at Newfoundland while d'Happart was onboard, and its cargo was confiscated. In 1806, Babin accused d'Happart of owing him money, and d'Happart was arrested and bound in a Philadelphia debtor's prison from 1807 to 1808. These materials are in French and English.
  - Passport, January 28, 1804 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1807 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1807 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1807 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1807 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1808 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1808 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1808 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1808 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1808 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Business Correspondence while in France, 1804-1808 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Litigation regarding the Brig Betsy, July-September 1805 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - James Madison to Joseph d'Happart, May 8, 1806 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - L. F. Babin to d'Happart, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - L. F. Babin Accounts, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - L. F. Babin Accounts, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Import Accounts with Joseph Thebeaud (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Import Accounts with Joseph Thebeaud, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Import Accounts with Joseph Thebeaud, 1804-1806 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Import Accounts with Simon Chaudron & Co., 1805-1807 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Import Accounts with Simon Chaudron & Co., 1805-1807 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Import Accounts with Simon Chaudron & Co., 1805-1807 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Import Accounts with Simon Chaudron & Co., 1805-1807 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Import Accounts, 1805-1808 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Imprisonment, 1807-1808 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - d'Happart's written testimony against Babin, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - d'Happart's accounts, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - d'Happart's accounts, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Albert Gallatin to d'Happart, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1808 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Personal Papers, 1800-1812; VI.
  D'Happart's personal papers consist of family correspondence, papers, and documents relating to his imprisonment and divorce. The Thompson Family papers document the family of his wife, Elizabeth Thompson St. Leger d'Happart. The Thomas family papers include family correspondence, and business agreements going back to a 1768 agreement for the delivery of beef cattle to Fort Pitt.
  Later correspondence between d'Happart and Elizabeth is characterized by antagonism over shared property and custody of their children, particularly their oldest son. It is unclear how public their marital conflicts were, but Elizabeth's petition for a divorce was granted by the governor of Pennsylvania in 1815. D'Happart contested the divorce, hoping that the governor would instead favor d'Happart's own competing divorce petition.
  - Thompson family papers, 1800-1801 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Thompson family papers, 1800-1801 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Thompson family papers, 1800-1801 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Thompson family papers, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Thompson family papers, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)